Okay, so now that we've seen JNAI and how to use it, let's look at bigger concepts around JNAI,
more theoretical, but their importance understand and the exam can ask you things about it.
So first is the process of tokenization. It's the idea of converting raw text into a sequence
of tokens. What does that mean? Well, here is a sentence. Wow, learning it was with the
fun is immensely fun. And here we have different ways of converting this words into tokens.
So we can do word-based tokenization. And the text is going to be split into individual words,
or we can have subword tokenization. And some words sometimes can be split too,
which is very helpful for long words. And for the model, you have less number of tokens,
because some tokens, for example, you say unacceptable is acceptable with you and in the beginning.
And so therefore, you just need to understand that un is a negative and acceptable is the token
acceptable. Hopefully that makes sense. So you can experiment at opening our website called tokenizer
and I put the sentence while learning it was just a fun is immensely fun. As you can see,
the while was a token. The comma itself is a token as well, learning it was with step
analysis. So step and was split into because probably step and step and step are very close.
Step is just my diminutive and un is probably just a French way of having my name. So it was split.
Maric right now are is being split as well, probably an error, but the model will figure this out
as it goes. And then is immensely fun. All of these are tokens and as well, the exclamation
point is also a token. So tokenization is converting this words into tokens because now each token
has an ID and it's much more easier to deal with IDs than to deal with the broad text itself.
So the context window is super important. This is the number of tokens that an
NLM can consider when generating text. So different models have different context windows and so
the larger the context window, the more information and coherence. And so it's kind of a race now
to have the greatest context window because the more context window you have, the more information
you can feed to your JNAI model. So if you look at GPT for turbo, it's 128,000 tokens, cloud 2,100,000
tokens. But for example, Google Gemini 1.5 Pro has 1 million tokens and up to 10 million token in the
context window in research. And that means that for one million token, you can have a one-hour
video fed to your model or 11 hours of audio or over 30,000 lines of code or 700,000 words.
So this is very important because well, this really tells us that it's a very important factor.
Now, when you have a large context window, I will say you're going to get more benefit out of it,
but it will require more memory and more processing power, of course, and therefore it may cost
a little more. So when you consider a model, the context window is going to be probably the first
factor to consider, making sure that it fits your use case. Next, we have the concept of embeddings.
So we've seen that a little bit with rag, but now we're going to go deep into how that works.
So the idea is that you want to create vector and a vector is an array of numerical values,
so many numerical values out of text images or audio. So for example, let's take some texts
and we have the cat set on the mat. So first, we're going to do tokenization. So each word in this
example is going to be extracted. The cat set on the mat. And then because we have tokenization,
every word is going to be converted into a token ID. It's just a dictionary that says that
the word there is a 165 and so on. Next, we're going to have an embeddings model. So this is where
we're going to create a vector for each token. So as you can see here, the word cats, the token cats,
if I may say, is going to be converted into a vector of many values here 0.025 and so on.
And the word that is going to have its own vector and the vectors can be very big. It could be
100 values if we wanted to and all these vectors are going to be stored in a vector database.
So why do we convert these tokens into vectors? Well, when we have the vectors with a very high
dimensionality, we can actually encode many features for one input token. So we can have the
meaning of the word. We can have the syntactic role, the sentiment, if it's a positive or negative
word and so much more. And so the models is able to capture a lot of information about the word
just by storing it into a high dimensionality vector. And this is what's used for vector databases
and RAG. Finally, because embeddings model can be easily searchable thanks to nearest neighbor
capability in vector databases, it is a very good way to use an embeddings model to power a search
application. And that is something that can come up in the exam. So I will do my best to show you this.
So words that have a semantic relationship that means they're similar will have similar embeddings.
So if we take the token, dog, puppy, cat and houses, and we make a vector say with 100 dimension
in them. So we may have 100 numerical values for each and every word or token. And so of course,
for us, it's very difficult as humans to visualize 100 dimensions, we're very good at two dimensions.
It's a sheet of paper. Three dimensions, we're very good at it because we can visualize things
with our eyes in three dimensions. But 100 dimensions is very difficult. And so to visualize
these things, sometimes we do what's called a dimensionality reduction. So we reduce these 100
dimensions, for example, two or three dimensions. So if we did it, for example, we would see
something like this. And in this two dimension diagram, we see that it looks like a puppy and a dog
are related. Yes, because a puppy is a small dog. And we look like the cat is not too far away
from a dog. Well, that's because it's an animal. But houses is very different. So it's going to
be far away on that diagram. So of course, with two dimensions, we don't capture any kind of
subtleness. But when we have 100 dimensions, we can really say which words relate to each other
and why. Another way to visualize a high dimension vector is to use colors. So for example, we use
color embedding and say each combination of numbers is going to make a color. And visually,
we can see, for example, in this very simplified one, that the puppy and the dog, they're very
similar because they have very similar colors. But house is very different. And so intuitively,
you can say that, yes, there is a semantic relationship between tokens with similar embeddings.
And that's why we use them. And that's why once we have them in a vector database,
we can then do a similarity search on the vector database. So we give a dog and automatically
we'll be able to pull out all the tokens that have a similar embedding as the dog. And that's it.
So let's say for more concepts on gen AI, but they appear at the exam. So hopefully now you
understand them, you'll be all good then. I hope you liked it. And I will see you in the next lecture.